<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>OpenSourcerer.eu - Open Source</title>
    <subtitle>Lars Marowsky-Brée on Free, Libre, and Open Source, Software Engineering, and IT</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://opensourcerer.eu/tags/open-source/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensourcerer.eu"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2025-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://opensourcerer.eu/tags/open-source/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>A New Compact</title>
        <published>2025-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensourcerer.eu/a-new-compact/"/>
        <id>https://opensourcerer.eu/a-new-compact/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensourcerer.eu/a-new-compact/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;learning-about-a-new-license&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#learning-about-a-new-license&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: learning-about-a-new-license&quot;&gt;Learning about a new license&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;social.vivaldi.net&#x2F;@lproven&quot;&gt;Liam Proven&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; brought the
&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;smallandnearlysilent.com&#x2F;baba-yaga&#x2F;LICENSE.txt&quot;&gt;Baba Yaga license&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
to my attention via &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;social.vivaldi.net&#x2F;@lproven&#x2F;115135292511567427&quot;&gt;Mastodon&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The field of endeavor and non-commercial restrictions alas will prevent this
brilliant piece of work from being widely adopted, which is a shame.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;mastodon.social&#x2F;@etchedpixels&#x2F;115135408071881673&quot;&gt;an thread with Alan Cox&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
he and I came up with two additional stanzas to incorporate attribution and warranty exclusions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I am unsure whether the original license&#x27;s preamble allows mere mortals to
iterate upon it, nevertheless, here is my second edition with some tweaks.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am very sorely tempted indeed to adopt it as the license for this website.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-new-compact&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-new-compact&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-new-compact&quot;&gt;The new compact&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;preamble&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#preamble&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: preamble&quot;&gt;Preamble&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By ancient rites, this work is bound,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
No mortal hand may twist it &#x27;round.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;terms-of-use&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#terms-of-use&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: terms-of-use&quot;&gt;Terms of Use&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Permission granted: to mend and make,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
To copy, share, for spirit&#x27;s sake.&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
Yet mark: no coin, no profit gained,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
Shall taint this magic, unrestrained.&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
Removed not shall all names be,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
as thou pass it onwards free.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#disclaimer&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: disclaimer&quot;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Provided &quot;as is,&quot; without a truth,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
No crone will blame, if ill, forsooth.&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
This work is dire and scribed for fun,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
Of warranties thus I grant you none.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;enforcement&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#enforcement&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: enforcement&quot;&gt;Enforcement&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pact by moonlight, strongly spun,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
Binds souls if greed hath now been won.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;cost&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#cost&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: cost&quot;&gt;Cost&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The threads are spun, the spell complete,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
No greed, lest curses, you shall meet.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Free, Libre, Open - Ethical?</title>
        <published>2024-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2024-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensourcerer.eu/free-open-ethical/"/>
        <id>https://opensourcerer.eu/free-open-ethical/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensourcerer.eu/free-open-ethical/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;tl-dr&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#tl-dr&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: tl-dr&quot;&gt;TL;DR&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Free, Libre, and Open Source freedoms, when treated as dogma, do harm.
To truly serve our values, the &quot;open&quot; software community must not only
do more but differently.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#introduction&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2012, I spent May Day (of all days) as a speaker and attendee at the
Linux Foundation&#x27;s Enterprise End User Summit in New York, hosted at the
New York Stock Exchange. On my way to the venue, we had to pass through
police cordons and, theoretically, protesters. Remember, the Occupy Wall
Street protests?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the opening keynote, the CEO of NYSE thanked us as developers and
a community for how Linux and Open Source had been instrumental in
bringing down the cost of trades, and how this enabled trades to go from
several minutes per trade to many thousands of trades per minute and
High Frequency Trading.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember swallowing hard; feeling complicit. Many of us sympathized
with the protesters&#x27;s perspective - yet there we were, taking
celebratory photos on the trading floor that evening, and optimizing the
machine that kept it all ticking.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happens when the tools we created to further our freedoms end up
enabling outcomes that contradict our values?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-free-and-open-source-software&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#why-free-and-open-source-software&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: why-free-and-open-source-software&quot;&gt;Why Free and Open Source Software?&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came to this community because I believed (and still do) that, given
the importance of software in our world, our society, our daily lives,
we must have agency. It must not be a black box to us, and we must have
the rights to inspect, understand, and modify it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also believed (and still do) that, for the vast majority of all use
cases, building software collaboratively and openly (or at least having
the option to) is the most effective method for society as a whole, but
also sustainable technology and business.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We build an ever growing, ever improving public commons, fostering
progress.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-loss-of-innocence&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-loss-of-innocence&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-loss-of-innocence&quot;&gt;The loss of innocence&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I am also no longer sixteen. I&#x27;ve built my career on Free,
Libre, and Open Source Software; I&#x27;ve seen people implement
bait-and-switch schemes on licensing, CLAs, exploitative practices that
only consume and never give anything back or even undercut those who do
(the trick to get really rich in capitalism is to exploit externalities
until - if - regulation catches up with you), or pay the maintainers
peanuts or nothing. (We have all seen &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;xkcd.com&#x2F;2347&#x2F;&quot;&gt;the famous XKCD
comic&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More so, I&#x27;ve also seen quite a few political turns and shifts, not all
of them progressive, but more and more reactionary backlashes. I&#x27;ve seen
how big tech has contributed and profited from this. I know exactly who
&lt;em&gt;also&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; wants big data systems.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expecting perfect alignment on everything would, indeed, be unrealistic
and detrimental; we need &lt;em&gt;some&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; resilience and elasticity in the face of
differences. With those who are somewhat neutral and where we have
complex nuanced differences of opinion and taste or reconcilable matters
of policy, sure. &lt;em&gt;The truth is rarely pure and never simple.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I do not want my work to enable those with whom I have a truly
fundamental systemic incompatibility; such as whose personhood is valid,
whose love is valid, whose choices are valid.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;free-and-open-source-software&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#free-and-open-source-software&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: free-and-open-source-software&quot;&gt;Free and Open Source Software&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still believe that Free, Libre, and Open Source Software is much more
compatible with my values than proprietary modes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But these principles are not just the bare minimum: they actively
constrain our ability to safeguard our values.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;unfettered-unrestricted&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#unfettered-unrestricted&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: unfettered-unrestricted&quot;&gt;Unfettered, unrestricted&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because one aspect the Free Software Foundation and the Open Source
Initiative agree on is that it must be free to use for any purpose; be
it the &lt;em&gt;for any kind of person or organization to use it on any kind of
computer system, for any kind of overall job and purpose&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; of the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Free Software Foundation (2024), “What is Free Software?”, GNU.org. Accessed: 2024-11-15&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.gnu.org&#x2F;philosophy&#x2F;free-sw.en.html#four-freedoms&quot;&gt;FSF&#x27;s
0th Freedom&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, or the &lt;em&gt;No Discrimination Against Persons or Groups&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
&amp;amp; &lt;em&gt;6 No Discrimination Against Field of Endeavor&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
of the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;OSI (2007), “The Open Source Definition v1.9”. Accessed: 2024-11-15&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource.org&#x2F;osd&quot;&gt;Open Source Definition&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A project that, say, allowed its use for commercial purposes only if the
company paid all its employees at least 10% above minimum wage?
Not to be embedded in weapons of mass destruction?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not Free Software. Not Open Source Software.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;OSI (2024), “Frequently Asked Questions”. Accessed: 2024-11-15&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource.org&#x2F;faq#evil&quot;&gt;The OSI is very, very clear on this.&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(It is somewhat ironic that the OSI would rather allow something to
claim the Open Source branding despite &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Open Source Initiative, “OSAID FAQ”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;hackmd.io&#x2F;@opensourceinitiative&#x2F;osaid-faq#Why-do-you-allow-the-exclusion-of-some-training-data&quot;&gt;its sources not being made
public&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (for purported ethical&#x2F;privacy considerations, no less!) than
allow ethical considerations to affect the use and distribution of
software when that might impede business. &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Marowsky-Brée (2024-11), “Notes on Open Source AI Definition”&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensourcerer.eu&#x2F;osaid-v1-0-notes&#x2F;&quot;&gt;I have written about this
recently&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, as have many others.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must ask: can a freedom go too far? As seen above, the FSF and OSI
have the same answer as those who conflate freedom of speech with
freedom from accountability.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if only it were so simple; we could focus on the nerdy intricacies
of our code and lose ourselves in a world we can control; rather than
having to consider what the tools we build enable, and whether or not we
may be accountable; if not legally, but to ourselves.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, their position is limited externally already; obviously, it
does not trump applicable law. We just don&#x27;t get to add additional
friction and constraints.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If, as a software developer or contributor, I can&#x27;t formally forbid my
work to be used for mass murder without being excluded from the
currently largest software community, does that not strike you as
strange?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see here a variant of the paradox of tolerance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;digression-who-are-we&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#digression-who-are-we&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: digression-who-are-we&quot;&gt;Digression: Who are &quot;we&quot;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this text, I&#x27;ve referenced &quot;us&quot; repeatedly, without ever defining it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that is a question worth exploring, because &quot;the&quot; Free, Libre,
and Open Source community is made up of many diverse individuals and
groups with different backgrounds, motivations, goals, beliefs, ethics;
&lt;em&gt;Open&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; vs &lt;em&gt;Free&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is an example of overlapping but significantly
diverging principles that yet mostly are able to join up for a greater
goal.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This would be even more prominent if we exposed more of our beliefs and
values; we would see more fractures in &quot;our&quot; groups. Who do we really
want to be &quot;we&quot; with?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no single &lt;em&gt;we&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, not one truly unified community. That is part
of the pretence we need to go beyond, even if the shorthand is useful in
communication. &quot;We&quot; are individuals with compatible enough shared goals
and values forming groups to further those, and then compatible enough
groups joining up to form larger alliances. There will always be some
friction.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;tangent-license-compatibility&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#tangent-license-compatibility&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: tangent-license-compatibility&quot;&gt;Tangent: license compatibility&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One reason why this is opposed is that a proliferation of terms and
conditions would make it difficult to determine whether multiple
licenses are compatible and the works can be combined in certain ways.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone working on Free, Libre, Open Source software, myself included,
will concur with this. Most software engineering degrees fail to prepare
us for arguing about what is or is not a derivative work, an aggregate,
fair use, or the intricacies of how GPL, LGPL, AGPL, Apache, Mozilla,
MIT, BSD differ, often in multiple versions. I suspect many of us had
&lt;em&gt;fun&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; calls with lawyers that we could have done without.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is, however, a flimsy reason to insist on doing nothing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modular systems, compatibility matrices, formalizing the most common
terms are possible and, at this point, honestly would not make the
situation all that much more complicated.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;endeavours-for-more-ethical-terms&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#endeavours-for-more-ethical-terms&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: endeavours-for-more-ethical-terms&quot;&gt;Endeavours for more ethical terms&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are already efforts to address this, such as the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Organization for Ethical Source, “The Hippocratice License”. Accessed: 2024-11-15&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;firstdonoharm.dev&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Hippocratic
License for Open Source Communities&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which strives to align
technology with their values and offer a modular build for your own
terms.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alas, their adoption suffers from the challenge that a lot of the
funding and effort flowing into the Free, Libre, and Open Source
communities is controlled by those prioritizing profits over principles.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, not all organizations are bound by shareholder primacy, profit
maximization, or the military-surveillance complex.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unions, cooperatives, public sector institutions, non-profits, hobbyist
individuals or communities, and even ethically-minded businesses could
lead the way in trialling and adopting such terms.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;freedom-of-association&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#freedom-of-association&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: freedom-of-association&quot;&gt;Freedom of Association&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there is something else you - we - can do: we don&#x27;t have to
associate with those who endanger our values.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of our communities have codes of conduct and contributor guidelines
already. Let&#x27;s strengthen those. Take a stand.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have the right to refuse interactions, contributions, patches,
reports, sponsorships, or affiliations with individuals or organizations
whose values, policies, or practices irreconcilably conflict with ours.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our ethics and values can absolutely be loud, visible, and
inconvenient.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe the best choice of licensing for your project really is one that
follows the Free, Open Source tenets. Maybe you can&#x27;t control the
choice. And yes, that means they could still use or fork the project.
But that doesn&#x27;t mean you have got to help further. Throw some sand
into the machine.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider adopting ethical practices that go beyond Free, Libre, and Open
Source. Demand them from those you associate with.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be however patient in the face of imperfection. People will try and fall
short; you, me, them. We exist in the world, and even when we change it,
change is not instant.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should come as no surprise that this, too, is already externally
restricted via national and international law and regulations, see for
example &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Corbet (2024), “Several Russian developers lose kernel maintainership status”, LWN.net. Accessed: 2024-11-15&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;lwn.net&#x2F;Articles&#x2F;995186&#x2F;&quot;&gt;the Linux kernel&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. The governments will absolutely have
their say; the idea that everyone is invited into every group is,
frankly, naïve.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;free-and-open-source-won-t-save-us&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#free-and-open-source-won-t-save-us&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: free-and-open-source-won-t-save-us&quot;&gt;Free and Open Source won&#x27;t save us&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Free and Open Source as they are and by themselves do not lead to a
fairer world.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to evolve beyond those rigid and supposedly &quot;neutral&quot;
approaches; it is not just commercial exploitation which open-washes our
communities (and where I believe that the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;sfconservancy.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Software Freedom
Conservancy&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; comes out ahead in their stance
over OSI&#x27;s pragmatism), but viewing software in isolation from the rest
of society would be reductionist. To insist on &quot;neutrality&quot; is in itself
a partisan position.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To quote the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;ethicalsource.dev&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Organization for Ethical
Source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;The true measure of success for
open source technologies is real-world impact: how what we co-create
promotes positive social, cultural, and political change.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything public is politic. The only people who can &quot;confidently&quot; say
that technology should be kept free of politics are those privileged
enough to be safe either way; or at least believe themselves to be. And
without empathy or awareness for the others. Do not yield to their
demands of amorality.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amorality in the face of injustice is immorality. &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Whelchel (1986), “Is Technology Neutral?”, IEEE. Accessed: 2024-11-15&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;ieeexplore.ieee.org&#x2F;document&#x2F;5010049&quot;&gt;Technology is not
neutral&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crafting perfect terms and licenses may well be impossible, but that is
no excuse for complete inaction. Instead, we must experiment, refine,
and adopt frameworks that align technology with our ethics.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, I visited the German Museum of Technology. One exhibit is a
Hollerith tabulating machine.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#sources&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;!-- Don&#x27;t come at me how ugly this is, you know how much willpower it
took not to disappear on a side quest of citation mgmt in Zola --&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[1]: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;OSI (2007), “The Open Source Definition v1.9”. Accessed: 2024-11-15&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource.org&#x2F;osd&quot;&gt;OSI (2007), “The Open Source Definition v1.9”. Accessed: 2024-11-15&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2]: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Free Software Foundation (2024), “What is Free Software?”, GNU.org. Accessed: 2024-11-15&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.gnu.org&#x2F;philosophy&#x2F;free-sw.en.html#four-freedoms&quot;&gt;Free Software Foundation (2024), “What is Free Software?”, GNU.org. Accessed: 2024-11-15&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[3]: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Open Source Initiative, “OSAID FAQ”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;hackmd.io&#x2F;@opensourceinitiative&#x2F;osaid-faq#Why-do-you-allow-the-exclusion-of-some-training-data&quot;&gt;Open Source Initiative, “OSAID FAQ”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[4]: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Marowsky-Brée (2024-11), “Notes on Open Source AI Definition”&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensourcerer.eu&#x2F;osaid-v1-0-notes&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Marowsky-Brée (2024-11), “Notes on Open Source AI Definition”&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[5]: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Organization for Ethical Source, “The Hippocratice License”. Accessed: 2024-11-15&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;firstdonoharm.dev&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Organization for Ethical Source, “The Hippocratice License”. Accessed: 2024-11-15&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[6]: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Whelchel (1986), “Is Technology Neutral?”, IEEE. Accessed: 2024-11-15&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;ieeexplore.ieee.org&#x2F;document&#x2F;5010049&quot;&gt;Whelchel (1986), “Is Technology Neutral?”, IEEE. Accessed: 2024-11-15&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[7]: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;OSI (2024), “Frequently Asked Questions”. Accessed: 2024-11-15&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource.org&#x2F;faq#evil&quot;&gt;OSI (2024), “Frequently Asked Questions”. Accessed: 2024-11-15&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[8]: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Corbet (2024), “Several Russian developers lose kernel maintainership status”, LWN.net. Accessed: 2024-11-15&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;lwn.net&#x2F;Articles&#x2F;995186&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Corbet (2024), “Several Russian developers lose kernel maintainership status”, LWN.net. Accessed: 2024-11-15&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;!-- 
- \[1\]: [Author, “”, where. Accessed: 2024-11-15][1]

[1]:  &quot;Author, “”, where. Accessed: 2024-11-15&quot;
 --&gt;
&lt;!-- 
- \[1\]: [Author, “”, where. Accessed: 2024-11-15][1]

[1]:  &quot;Author, “”, where. Accessed: 2024-11-15&quot;
 --&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>OSI&#x27;s Open Source AI Definition v1.0</title>
        <published>2024-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2024-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensourcerer.eu/osaid-v1-0-notes/"/>
        <id>https://opensourcerer.eu/osaid-v1-0-notes/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensourcerer.eu/osaid-v1-0-notes/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#introduction&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Artificial Intelligence (AI) and Machine Learning (ML), such as
Generative AI and Large Language Models (LLMs), have, for better or
worse, a growing impact in shaping critical societal outcomes; from
healthcare via finance to public safety in general (consider
self-driving cars) - as well as in our every day lives as individuals.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without openness and transparency, AI could perpetuate unchecked biases
that shape public policy, healthcare, and legal outcomes. Without
openness and the ability to modify the systems that influence and run
our lives, we are robbed of freedom and agency.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the jury is still out whether they can deliver on their promises
in the real world, there&#x27;s no denying that AI&#x2F;ML&#x2F;LLM-based systems are
replacing, or at the very least augmenting, traditional Information
Technology systems.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the traditional IT world, we have now familiar and highly successful
paradigms of Free, Libre, and Open Source Software that strive to ensure
our rights and abilities to not just &lt;strong&gt;Use&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, but also to &lt;strong&gt;Study&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;,
&lt;strong&gt;Modify&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Share&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For individuals and society at large not to be at the questionable mercy
of inscrutable blackboxes (often proprietary, and under the control of
for-profit businesses), such rights are fundamental to maintain our
digital sovereignty.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If our digital human rights are not sufficient arguments, Free, Libre,
and Open Source Software Systems nowadays provide &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;M. Hoffmann, F. Nagle, and Y. Zhou, “The Value of Open Source Software,” SSRN Journal, 2024.&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.ssrn.com&#x2F;abstract=4693148&quot;&gt;inconceivable value
for the global economy&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus arises the necessity to protect those freedoms in AI&#x2F;ML-driven
systems.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Open Source Initiative (OSI)&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; has just
released the first version of their &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Open Source Initiative, “The Open Source AI Definition – 1.0”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource.org&#x2F;ai&#x2F;open-source-ai-definition&quot;&gt;Open Source AI Definition
(OSAID)&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and its associated &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Open Source Initiative, “OSAID FAQ”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;hackmd.io&#x2F;@opensourceinitiative&#x2F;osaid-faq&quot;&gt;Frequently Asked Questions (FAQ)&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The OSI declares themselves to the &lt;em&gt;&quot;the authority&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; that defines Open
Source&quot;, and &lt;em&gt;the steward&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; of the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource.org&#x2F;definition&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Open Source
Definition&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. It is fair to say that
they are one of the most influential organizations in this space, with
broad impact on the IT industry, communities, and political policy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means we must hold OSI&#x27;s release of version one point zero, which
is no longer declared a draft asking for comments but for active
endorsement, to a rather high standard and critically evaluate whether
it manages to uphold and protect the values behind Open Source Software
(that they do not wish to uphold the values of Free Software in full we
already know), and what might be needed to address any gaps or misses.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not the first such writing, and I want to give explicit
acknowledgement to the sources and authors referenced at the end for
influencing my thinking. The tenor of the positions from the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Free Software Foundation, “FSF is working on freedom in machine learning applications”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.fsf.org&#x2F;news&#x2F;fsf-is-working-on-freedom-in-machine-learning-applications&quot;&gt;FSF&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or
the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Software Freedom Conservancy, “Open Source AI Definition Erodes the Meaning of Open Source”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;sfconservancy.org&#x2F;blog&#x2F;2024&#x2F;oct&#x2F;31&#x2F;open-source-ai-definition-osaid-erodes-foss&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Software Freedom Conservancy&#x27;s aspirational stance&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, but also
other &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;S. Vaughan-Nichols, “We have an official open-source AI definition now, but the fight is far from over”, ZDNET. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.zdnet.com&#x2F;article&#x2F;we-have-an-official-open-source-ai-definition-now-but-the-fight-is-far-from-over&#x2F;&quot;&gt;respected&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;tante, “Does Open Source AI really exist?”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;tante.cc&#x2F;2024&#x2F;10&#x2F;16&#x2F;does-open-source-ai-really-exist&#x2F;&quot;&gt;individuals&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, clearly shows that advocates
expect the OSI to do better.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-positive-intentions-and-achievements&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-positive-intentions-and-achievements&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-positive-intentions-and-achievements&quot;&gt;The Positive Intentions and Achievements&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OSI states to have engaged with diverse stakeholders - who will not
always have had perfectly aligned interests and positions. Anyone who
has ever worked on any sort of large collaborative definition effort
recognizes the impossibility to achieve everyone&#x27;s goals without often
painful compromises. Especially when global stakeholders from all across
the industry meet ethical and moral concerns.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is always easy to criticize someone else&#x27;s work - after it has been
published. We would not be having this discourse right now if OSI
hadn&#x27;t, and it behoves us to acknowledge this, too, despite criticism.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, providing an initial framework for &quot;Open Source AI&quot; and addressing
a previously largely undefined space is an important step that I do not
wish to discount. OSI is providing a baseline to argue on.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key goal of OSAID is not merely to address the &quot;traditional&quot; source
code used to build, train, run, and operate AI&#x2F;ML systems; it would have
been easy for OSI to limit themselves to this aspect which most closely
aligns with their original scope and experiences. Instead, it recognizes
and aims to cover the multiple components that together form an
AI&#x2F;ML-based system.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;software-source-code&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#software-source-code&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: software-source-code&quot;&gt;Software Source Code&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Requiring the &quot;complete&quot; software source to be made available
under an OSI-approved license is the obvious application of FLOSS
principles to AI systems. This is fairly broadly phrased, including even
supporting libraries and the model architecture.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be nice if this included explicit requirements for the (kernel)
drivers as well, and there&#x27;s always the question where &quot;software&quot; ends
for GPUs and other hardware components that implement quite complex
firmware. Or whether this covers all the layers through which a user
interacts with the system in the end (and which might further process
the results).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is indeed the minimal standard any &quot;Open Source AI&quot; system must
meet. Though if the scope was limited to this, I&#x27;d argue we have not
gone beyond anything previously sufficiently covered.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how successful is OSI&#x27;s address of the new components?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;critique&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#critique&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: critique&quot;&gt;Critique&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-data&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-data&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-data&quot;&gt;The Data&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Positively, the OSAID &lt;em&gt;does&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; outline guidelines that clearly make
systems that comply with them more &quot;open&quot; than those that do not.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Describing the data used in fair detail, its provenance, the sourcing,
the processing, labelling, whether public or from &lt;em&gt;third parties
(including for fee)&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; &lt;sub&gt;(which is a more polite way to say proprietary
and non-free)&lt;&#x2F;sub&gt; is a significant step up from those AI&#x2F;ML systems
where we have no idea.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, here is also where OSAID falls crucially, critically short of
its stated goal: it does not even &lt;em&gt;recommend&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; that the training data
should be free&#x2F;open by default, much less &lt;em&gt;require&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike traditional software, AI&#x2F;ML systems derive their &lt;strong&gt;main&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; logic
and function from training on their &lt;em&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; data. Not providing those
denies some of the core freedoms and rights.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, traditional systems also use external assets (such as media) that
is not always governed by the same open&#x2F;free rights as the source code,
but it was still possible to inspect how they processed them. (And it is
worth pointing out that some voices would not consider even such
systems &quot;open&quot; if they had critical non-open&#x2F;non-free dependencies.)
This data is usually what they operate &lt;em&gt;on&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; or what configures the
system, not the core of the system &lt;em&gt;itself&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Open Source Initiative, “OSAID FAQ”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;hackmd.io&#x2F;@opensourceinitiative&#x2F;osaid-faq&quot;&gt;OSAID FAQ&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; elaborates that not all data &lt;em&gt;can&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; be free or open,
and perhaps not &lt;em&gt;everywhere&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; - such as, say, confidential medical data,
or situations where legislation differ globally. And that is a clearly
valid. &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Free Software Foundation, “FSF is working on freedom in machine learning applications”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.fsf.org&#x2F;news&#x2F;fsf-is-working-on-freedom-in-machine-learning-applications&quot;&gt;Even the Free Software Foundation concedes this aspect,&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
arguing that nonfree AI&#x2F;ML systems could still be just.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet - to be able to assess whether a system was trained for a particular
situation, whether its training data contains any relevant biases that
might produce discriminatory results, that can &lt;em&gt;only&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; be reasonably done
if access to this data is open.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;osi-approved-terms&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#osi-approved-terms&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: osi-approved-terms&quot;&gt;OSI-approved terms&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another shortcoming for OSAID to be truly meaningful is that, for even
the limited &quot;data information&quot; we get as well as the model parameters
and configuration settings, it specifies only that they &quot;shall be made
available under &lt;em&gt;OSI-approved terms&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&quot;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which, the FAQ elaborates somewhat unhelpfully, does &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (yet?)
refer to any defined legal mechanisms, and can thus at best be seen as
an aspirational statement.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A typical OSI-approved license that would govern source code does not
directly apply, since data is not software as such in the eyes of the
law, courts, and international treaties. Yet, the Linux Foundation has
developed &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;The Linux Foundation, “Community Data License Agreement - Sharing, Version 1.0”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;cdla.dev&#x2F;sharing-1-0&#x2F;&quot;&gt;terms that might serve&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and for the OSI to suggest not
anything here is disappointing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this to supposedly govern the key components beyond software source
code (which, I might remind the reader, is the entire &lt;em&gt;point&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;) it is far
too vague.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-description-of-the-data-is-not-the-data&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#a-description-of-the-data-is-not-the-data&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: a-description-of-the-data-is-not-the-data&quot;&gt;A description of the data is not the data&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To summarize:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; for the components that go beyond traditional software
systems, the OSAID does neither require their full openness &lt;em&gt;nor&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
provide concrete guidance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;limited-transparency-and-ability-to-audit&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#limited-transparency-and-ability-to-audit&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: limited-transparency-and-ability-to-audit&quot;&gt;Limited Transparency and Ability to Audit&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key benefit of Open Source Software is the transparency to inspect and
audit a system&#x27;s behaviours, decisions, actions through its source
code.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This must imply access to all relevant components of our digital
systems, notably the training data.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is crucial for individuals and society to understand the systems
they&#x27;re interacting with or even controlled by. We must be able to
discover biases of all kinds - non-representative data sets,
discriminatory data, lack of coverage for critical scenarios, or even
intentional data manipulation that introduces malicious exploits.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running experiments on the resulting models remains necessary (&quot;has the
system learned the intended correlations&quot;), but not sufficient. It is
already not feasible to thoroughly test traditional software; it is
similarly impossible to try and test a system whose points of
reference are unknown and opaque.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not spotting and correcting these may result in reproducing gender- or
ethnic-bias in generated imagery. It could be used to manipulate
financial decisions. In scenarios such as healthcare, policing, or
autonomous vehicles, it might prove fatal.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;hidden-data-hidden-exploitation&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#hidden-data-hidden-exploitation&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: hidden-data-hidden-exploitation&quot;&gt;Hidden data, hidden exploitation?&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As pointed out in &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;tante, “Does Open Source AI really exist?”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;tante.cc&#x2F;2024&#x2F;10&#x2F;16&#x2F;does-open-source-ai-really-exist&#x2F;&quot;&gt;this blog article by tante&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, there is another
reason to want to keep the training data secret, beyond valid privacy
and safety concerns. Not just from society, but also competitors, or
legitimate copyright holders. (The large ones; the small ones stand no
chance against the offenders anyway.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Namely: the data was not, in fact, sourced in compliance with all legal
and regulatory obligations, or at least is severely ethically or morally
contentious.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blog raises the rather plausible claim that &lt;em&gt;all&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; large data sets
are thus contaminated.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is &lt;em&gt;significantly&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; easier to hide behind a mere &quot;description&quot; of
the data or a barrier with contractual clauses attached, plus anyone
able to pay your high fee is likely similarly compromised. This saves
the companies from both public outrage and, worse, penalty payments or
regulatory fines.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tante also further explores this theme, which I highly recommend you
read and think through; even though I don&#x27;t necessarily agree with the
final conclusion: the conflict between Free, Libre, and Open Source
values and our rights versus profit-maximizing and exploitative
business models, aka un- or under-regulated capitalism with shareholder
primacy and venture capital, is very real.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This aspect is particularly ironic given that there&#x27;s suspicion that a
significant portion of AI&#x2F;ML&#x2F;LLM systems intended to assist with
software development and code generation are, indeed, trained on data
including code licensed under Free, Libre, and Open Source terms (or,
e.g., non-code assets that are governed by Creative Commons requiring
attribution and&#x2F;or explicitly excluding commercial use) and might be
going to significant lengths to obscure that in their output.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is impossible to tell if all you got was an &quot;Open Source&quot;
Model&#x2F;Weights (we cannot reverse the training process and make strong
assertions about the training data from the resulting model), or when
you can&#x27;t truly inspect the source data. Shouldn&#x27;t an &quot;Open Source AI&quot;
go to great lengths to explicitly safeguard the rights and shared values
of the Open Source Community?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;modifying-and-sharing&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#modifying-and-sharing&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: modifying-and-sharing&quot;&gt;Modifying and Sharing&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, the rights to Modify and Share are slightly less of a
priority in the holistic context of this critique (since they&#x27;d likely
also be resolved by addressing the core criticisms), but nonetheless
necessary. Again, these are greatly hindered by the weak requirements
and rights provided.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, models can be iteratively trained (depending on what &quot;OSI-approved
terms&quot; end up requiring), and that allows certain influences on their
behaviours. But that&#x27;s not the same as the ability to rebuild or retrain
another, modified model.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, this also needs to acknowledge that the training data can be huge;
not mere gigabytes, but exabytes. And that the hardware resources and
power requirements to train a model can be similarly vast. Not everyone
can aim to reproduce everything. But we also assume that for FLOSS in
general.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still: for an &quot;Open Source AI&quot; definition to provide so little guidance
on how to actually modify and share those modifications fails to address
half of the Four Freedoms.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;risk-of-open-washing-undermining-open-source&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#risk-of-open-washing-undermining-open-source&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: risk-of-open-washing-undermining-open-source&quot;&gt;Risk of Open-Washing - Undermining &quot;Open Source&quot;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why, in the light of all this, then the insistence to define such a
seemingly comprehensive term as &quot;Open Source AI&quot;?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OSI does not allow calling something &quot;Open Source Software&quot; if it just
comes with a description of what the source code looks like and where
you can pay for access to it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the only component of the system that is fully &quot;Open Source&quot; is the
software one, we should rather call this an &quot;AI&#x2F;ML system provided by
Open Source Software&quot;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This could lead to (further) undermining of the value of &quot;Open Source&quot;
to individuals and society, and in fact allow companies to use the
marketing branding of &quot;Open Source AI&quot; while, in fact, continuing
business as usual.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the Free, Libre, Open Source Software community has a
history with such term dilution: &quot;Open Source Software&quot; is a more
industry-pleasing alternative to &quot;Free Software&quot;; and calling
less-protective licenses &quot;more permissive&quot; was a stroke of marketing
genius for capitalist-value-extraction. (Some of the history is
referenced to in the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Software Freedom Conservancy, “Open Source AI Definition Erodes the Meaning of Open Source”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;sfconservancy.org&#x2F;blog&#x2F;2024&#x2F;oct&#x2F;31&#x2F;open-source-ai-definition-osaid-erodes-foss&#x2F;&quot;&gt;SFC blog post&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;superficial-marketing-term&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#superficial-marketing-term&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: superficial-marketing-term&quot;&gt;Superficial marketing term?&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The additional demands placed on companies to use the new label are not
onerous: it is already the default for most AI&#x2F;ML software development
and in many other areas of IT, given the clear economical benefits and
marketing value.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Describing the data sources is something a few regulatory efforts (see
next section) already request, and in line with the general move towards
strongly documented supply-chains and bills of materials.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a commercial perspective, a superficial definition is preferable to
one with teeth, since it allows for an easy marketing win: another
positive label to stick on the box.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there are possibly additional benefits - from a commercial
perspective, not necessarily from an individual and societal one:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;potential-implications-for-public-policy-and-regulation&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#potential-implications-for-public-policy-and-regulation&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: potential-implications-for-public-policy-and-regulation&quot;&gt;Potential implications for public policy and regulation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;European Parliament and Council, “Regulation (EU) 2024&#x2F;1689 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 13 June 2024 laying down harmonised rules on artificial intelligence and amending Regulations”, Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;data.europa.eu&#x2F;eli&#x2F;reg&#x2F;2024&#x2F;1689&#x2F;oj&#x2F;eng&quot;&gt;European Union&#x27;s Artificial Intelligence Act&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; outlines certain
transparency requirements for AI systems. However, it also lowers
certain standards for &quot;free and open license GPAI models&quot;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not inconceivable that a company might claim compliance with the
OSAID to benefit from these reduced requirements, bamboozling policy
makers and public decision makers by using a term defined by a respected
industry organization.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This demonstrates the need for a visionary definition that is a truer
representation of Free, Libre, and Open values - and those of our open
and democratic societies -, and one that is harder to subvert.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;tl-dr&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#tl-dr&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: tl-dr&quot;&gt;TL;DR&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Open Source AI Definition v1.0 claims to set out to address the need
for a definition of &quot;Open Source&quot; in the context of AI&#x2F;ML systems; but
it falls critically short, with potentially broad implications.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it stands, I can only conclude that &quot;Open Source AI&quot; is a somewhat
rushed marketing effort that does not actually deliver on what I would
expect or what I believe society needs for digital sovereignty and
safety. Much less our individual freedoms and rights, and further erodes
the proclaimed values.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A less charitable interpretation might be that the industry wanted a
&lt;del&gt;lobbying&lt;&#x2F;del&gt; pragmatic organisation to produce - and get endorsements
for to make it appear widely accepted - a weaker definition ahead of
public discourse and political regulation defining &quot;our&quot; requirements,
thereby shaping and steering the discourse in their commercial
interests. While I would not accuse any specific individual involved, we
need to be mindful of how this discourse is now primed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applications that have valid reasons for not making their sources
publicly accessible exist; data privacy around personal information and
medical data come to mind. For these systems to be just and aligned with
our (digital) human rights, they may not be able to be fully &quot;Open
Source&quot;; they then should not be called by this term. This is a tricky
but quite feasible balance to maintain and regulate, and they can still
be required to be reviewed by appointed and chartered experts; this is
not a new concept.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such valid concerns should not allow more common scenarios to take
advantage of them for their for-profit goals and marketing, and to lower
our baseline standards for openness transparency.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must protect the value of the &quot;Open Source&quot; term (such as it is).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the speed at which AI&#x2F;ML is adopted into critical infrastructure
and thus the urgent need to ensure its compatibility with our values,
&lt;em&gt;now&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is the time to set our direction; we cannot afford to rush this to
serve only industry stakeholders&#x27; needs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;where-to-next&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#where-to-next&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: where-to-next&quot;&gt;Where to next&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to create a nuanced and differentiated position beyond what
OSI&#x27;s OSAID delivers today. My personal highest hope is for &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Software Freedom Conservancy, “Open Source AI Definition Erodes the Meaning of Open Source”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;sfconservancy.org&#x2F;blog&#x2F;2024&#x2F;oct&#x2F;31&#x2F;open-source-ai-definition-osaid-erodes-foss&#x2F;&quot;&gt;the efforts
and aspirations of the Software Freedom Conservancy&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, who are well
respected, with a strong voice and history of upholding principled
positions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(And if you can, consider &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Software Freedom Conservancy, “Open Source AI Definition Erodes the Meaning of Open Source”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;sfconservancy.org&#x2F;blog&#x2F;2024&#x2F;oct&#x2F;31&#x2F;open-source-ai-definition-osaid-erodes-foss&#x2F;&quot;&gt;supporting Bradley M. Kuhn on the OSI Board
of Directors&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Whether OSI itself can be swayed or not is up for
debate; at the very least, we need to ensure their respective position
and background in &quot;the community&quot; (such as it exists) is better
understood by all.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it would be great if all of this could indeed be wrapped in a
single term, recognizing the complexity of the real world might require
addressing Open Data, Open Source, and Open Weights separately, or
perhaps with multiple tiers per component. A &lt;em&gt;truly&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; open and just
system would also need to somehow address the resource requirements;
freedoms must be exercisable in reality.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This could come together under the broad umbrella of &quot;Open Source AI&quot; in
the end; but when used without further qualification, this must at least
default to real openness for all covered components.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that the currently on-going dialogue in the community, industry,
media, as well as amongst advocates, researchers, ethicists, and policy
makers contributes to this effort.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please raise your own voice in demanding &lt;em&gt;fully&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; open AI&#x2F;ML systems
wherever possible and not just where commercially convenient.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We might see an improved &lt;em&gt;Open Source AI Definition, Version 2.0&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Or
need to adopt another organization&#x27;s guidebook, if OSI keeps their focus
on &lt;del&gt;industry palatability&lt;&#x2F;del&gt; pragmatism.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#sources&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;!-- Don&#x27;t come at me how ugly this is, you know how much willpower it
took not to disappear on a side quest of citation mgmt in Zola --&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[1]: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;S. Vaughan-Nichols, “We have an official open-source AI definition now, but the fight is far from over”, ZDNET. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.zdnet.com&#x2F;article&#x2F;we-have-an-official-open-source-ai-definition-now-but-the-fight-is-far-from-over&#x2F;&quot;&gt;S. Vaughan-Nichols, “We have an official open-source AI definition now, but the fight is far from over”, ZDNET. Accessed: 2024-11-02&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[2]: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Open Source Initiative, “OSAID FAQ”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;hackmd.io&#x2F;@opensourceinitiative&#x2F;osaid-faq&quot;&gt;Open Source Initiative, “OSAID FAQ”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[3]: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Open Source Initiative, “The Open Source AI Definition – 1.0”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource.org&#x2F;ai&#x2F;open-source-ai-definition&quot;&gt;Open Source Initiative, “The Open Source AI Definition – 1.0”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[4]: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Software Freedom Conservancy, “SFC Announces Aspirational Statement on LLM-backed generative AI for Programming”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;sfconservancy.org&#x2F;news&#x2F;2024&#x2F;oct&#x2F;25&#x2F;aspirational-on-llm-generative-ai-programming&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Software Freedom Conservancy, “SFC Announces Aspirational Statement on LLM-backed generative AI for Programming”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[5]: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;J. Brockmeier, “OSI readies controversial Open AI definition”, LWN.net. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;lwn.net&#x2F;Articles&#x2F;995159&#x2F;&quot;&gt;J. Brockmeier, “OSI readies controversial Open AI definition”, LWN.net. Accessed: 2024-11-02&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[6]: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Free Software Foundation, “FSF is working on freedom in machine learning applications”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.fsf.org&#x2F;news&#x2F;fsf-is-working-on-freedom-in-machine-learning-applications&quot;&gt;Free Software Foundation, “FSF is working on freedom in machine learning applications”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[7]: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;tante, “Does Open Source AI really exist?”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;tante.cc&#x2F;2024&#x2F;10&#x2F;16&#x2F;does-open-source-ai-really-exist&#x2F;&quot;&gt;tante, “Does Open Source AI really exist?”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[8]: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;M. Hoffmann, F. Nagle, and Y. Zhou, “The Value of Open Source Software,” SSRN Journal, 2024.&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.ssrn.com&#x2F;abstract=4693148&quot;&gt;M. Hoffmann, F. Nagle, and Y. Zhou, “The Value of Open Source Software,” SSRN Journal, 2024.&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[9]: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;The Linux Foundation, “Community Data License Agreement - Sharing, Version 1.0”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;cdla.dev&#x2F;sharing-1-0&#x2F;&quot;&gt;The Linux Foundation, “Community Data License Agreement - Sharing, Version 1.0”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[10]: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;European Parliament and Council, “Regulation (EU) 2024&#x2F;1689 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 13 June 2024 laying down harmonised rules on artificial intelligence and amending Regulations”, Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;data.europa.eu&#x2F;eli&#x2F;reg&#x2F;2024&#x2F;1689&#x2F;oj&#x2F;eng&quot;&gt;European Parliament and Council, “Regulation (EU) 2024&#x2F;1689 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 13 June 2024 laying down harmonised rules on artificial intelligence and amending Regulations”, Accessed: 2024-11-02&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[11]: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Software Freedom Conservancy, “Open Source AI Definition Erodes the Meaning of Open Source”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;sfconservancy.org&#x2F;blog&#x2F;2024&#x2F;oct&#x2F;31&#x2F;open-source-ai-definition-osaid-erodes-foss&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Software Freedom Conservancy, “Open Source AI Definition Erodes the Meaning of Open Source”. Accessed: 2024-11-02&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Introducing OpenSourcerer.eu</title>
        <published>2024-10-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2024-10-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://opensourcerer.eu/intro/"/>
        <id>https://opensourcerer.eu/intro/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://opensourcerer.eu/intro/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;welcome&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#welcome&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: welcome&quot;&gt;Welcome&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my - Lars Marowsky-Brée&#x27;s - new site!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My aim is to complement my social media and other channels with more
Free, Libre, Open Source, IT, tech focused content, as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensourcerer.eu&#x2F;about&#x2F;&quot;&gt;explained on the
about page&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in more detail.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tech-stack&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#tech-stack&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: tech-stack&quot;&gt;Tech stack&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I need the barrier to writing and posting an article to be reasonably
low, and I have very low requirements on functionality, features, and
design.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence, this site uses a &lt;em&gt;Static Site Generator&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, more specifically
&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;getzola.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Zola&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to generate the web presence from Markdown
formatted content.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I opted for this path over dynamic site builders since it just fits my
workflow and preferences better. Similarly, I recognize there are other
options than Zola.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitHub Pages, where I&#x27;m hosting this site mainly because of the very low
cost (zero is hard to beat, and while it is an &quot;unnecessary&quot;
entanglement with a US-based tech giant, I think the practical impact is
miniscule and easy to remove in the future if the need arises) and easy
integration with a text- &amp;amp; git-based workflow, offers Jekyll natively,
but I did in the past find that somewhat more tricky to use and build
the site locally for testing; and I had no interest in learning Ruby and
Gems.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most likely alternative would have been &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;gohugo.io&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Hugo&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
Yet, my needs are entirely trivial, and Zola just appealed to me more,
plus &lt;em&gt;if&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; I ever have to investigate something in the core code, it&#x27;d
allow me to learn some more Rust. Win-win!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while I have obviously immediately hit
&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;getzola&#x2F;zola&#x2F;issues&#x2F;2677&quot;&gt;one&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or
&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;zola.discourse.group&#x2F;t&#x2F;page-wide-data-shortcodes-macros&#x2F;2340&#x2F;2&quot;&gt;two&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
limitations, I&#x27;m still quite happy with this choice. Since all content
is based on Markdown, I assume a transition to something else in the
future would be straightforward anyway.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;future&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#future&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: future&quot;&gt;Future&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have no fixed schedule for content to appear on this site; since it&#x27;s
a hobbyist project besides my actual job and personal life, don&#x27;t expect
new content too frequently.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I have been known to &lt;del&gt;go off on rants when something annoys me&lt;&#x2F;del&gt;
have well-researched opinions on significant topics and an interest in
sharing those thoughts publicly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I look forward to engaging with y&#x27;all!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
